Finding Aid for Patterson Family papers, 1825-1931
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Patterson Family papers 1825-1931
Patterson family.
(in 4 boxes)
3 linear feet
852119 Aa 2
New York State and Ann Arbor, Michigan family; family correspondence, business papers, student notebooks, photograph albums.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Mrs. G. W. Patterson III (donor no. 328 ) and came to the library in 1937.
No further additions to the papers are expected.
The collection is open to research.
George W. Patterson, I, was born in Londonderry, New Hampshire on November 11, 1799. He moved to New York State in 1818 where he became engaged in a variety of manufacturing and agricultural pursuits. Politically active, Patterson was a member of the state assembly, 1832-1833 and 1835-1840. In 1841, he moved to Westfield, New York to take charge of the Chautauqua land office. He was elected lieutenant governor of New York in 1848. He also served one term in Congress, 1877 to 1879. He died October 15, 1879.
George W. Patterson, II, was a Westfield, New York businessman. He died in 1904.
George W. Patterson, III, was born in Corning, New York on February 1, 1864. He received his B.A. degree from Yale in 1884, his B.S. at the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1887, and his Ph.D. from the University of Munich in 1899. Patterson had come to Ann Arbor in 1889 as instructor in electrical engineering; in 1890, he was appointed instructor in physics; he was made assistant professor in 1891, junior professor in 1897. From 1901 to 1905, he was junior professor of electrical engineering; from 1905 to 1915 he was full professor. In 1915, he was made head of the department of engineering mechanics. In 1922 he was appointed assistant dean of the Colleges of Engineering and Architecture. He was made associate dean in 1928. He died May 22, 1930.
George W. Patterson, IV, was a graduate of Yale University, class of 1914, and a decorated soldier during World War I.
The Patterson family papers have been arranged as much as possible by family member name. To avoid confusion and because the name George Washington Patterson was passed down from father to son, the series names have been given a Roman numeral to distinguish one family member from another.
Subjects:
Europe--Description and travel.; Marshall (Mich.); New York (State)--Politics and government.; Patterson family.; Voyages and travels.; United States. Congress. House.; United States--Politics and government--1845-1861.; United States--Politics and government--1861-1865.; United States--Politics and government--1865-1900.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; Washington (D.C.); Whig Party (U.S.); World War, 1914-1918.; Yale University--Students.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
France.; Interiors.; Medical aspects of war.; Military facilities--France.; Patterson, George W. (George Washington), 1864-1930.; Troop movements.; War damage.; World War, 1914-1918.; Yale University.
Contributors:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Conkling, Roscoe, 1829-1888.; Dix, John Alden, 1860-1928.; Patterson, George Washington, 1799-1879.; Patterson, George W. (George Washington), 1864-1930.; Thompson, Richard W.; Weed, Thurlow, 1797-1882.
Genre Terms:
Aerial photographs.; Drawings.; Photographs.; Scrapbooks.
- George W. Patterson, I
  The papers of George W. Patterson I relates to family matters, his work with the Chautauqua land office, New York and national politics (including Whig Party affairs), and to his life in Washington, D.C. as a member of Congress.
  - Correspondence 1839-1879
    - 1839-1846 (Box 1)
    - January-July 1847 (Box 1)
    - August-December, 1847 (Box 1)
    - 1848 (Box 1)
    - January-March 1950 (Box 1)
    - April-June, 1850 (Box 1)
    - July-December, 1850 (Box 1)
    - 1851 (Box 1)
    - January-June, 1854 (Box 1)
    - July-December, 1854 (Box 1)
    - January-April, 1855 (Box 1)
    - May-December, 1855 (Box 1)
    - 1857 (Box 1)
    - 1874 (Box 1)
    - 1876 (Box 1)
    - 1877 (Box 1)
    - January 1878 (Box 1)
    - February-March 19, 1878 (Box 1)
    - 1879 (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous deeds, notes, etc. (Box 1)
  - Will 1879 (Box 1)
- George W. Patterson, II
  The George W. Patterson II papers relate to his business but are also of interest for the letters written to family and friends from various trips to Europe in the 1880s. There is some overlap with papers of his father.
  - Correspondence 1877-1889
    - 1877 (Box 2)
    - May-November, 1878 (Box 2)
    - December 1878 (Box 2)
    - 1879 (Box 2)
    - 1880-1882 (Box 2)
    - 1884-1887 (Box 2)
    - 1888-1889 (Box 2)
- George W. Patterson, III
  George W. Patterson III also wrote letters home while at school. Of note are those letters written from Germany while attending the University of Munich. This Patterson's papers also include his student notebooks from MIT and the University of Munich. There is some overlap with papers of his father.
  - Correspondence 1890-1931
    - 1890-1899 (Box 2)
    - 1900-1931 (Box 2)
  - Student notebooks from the University of Munich and the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 14 volumes (Box 2)
  - Manuscript of "Photometry" (Box 3)
  - Article, "The Torque between the Two Coils of an absolute Electrodynamometer" (Box 3)
  - Biographical sketch signed by Joseph A. Bursley, Arthur L. Cross and Herbert C. Sadler (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous: essays, reports, and memorabilia (Box 3)
  - Photographic portrait (Box 3)
- George Washington Patterson IV
  The George W. Patterson IV papers consist of a student scrapbook containing photographs and memorabilia accumulated while at Yale University. Another album relates to his service with the French during World War I.
  - Scrapbook/Album of postcard photographs and other memorabilia relating to his World War I service (Box 4)
  - Scrapbook/Album of photographs and memorabilia relating to student life at Yale University. (Box 4)
- Other papers
  The Other papers series includes genealogical material, scattered business papers, and mid-nineteenth century poems and essays.
  - Papers relating to Patterson family genealogy, 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Papers relating to the Westfield Cemetery Association (Box 3)
  - William Patterson Business papers 1825-1838 (Box 3)
  - Hannah W. Patterson business papers and correspondence 1882-1884 (Box 3)
  - Essays and poetry (author unknown; mid-19th century) (Box 3)
Related Material
The River Campus Libraries of the University of Rochester has an extensive collection of the papers of George W. Patterson I.